Guide to the Records of Office of Radio and Television RG 7.3.1
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of Radio and Television
1953-1985
RG 7.3.1
New York University Archives
12.5 linear feet (30 boxes)
The Office of Radio and Television was created in 1952 to oversee the development of University-sponsored and -produced radio and television programs. In addition to producing educational programs, the Office of Radio and Television advised NYU faculty members on developing their prospective programs. The office also acted as a liaison between NYU and the media. The collection contains administrative records detailing the evolution and impact of the Office of Radio and Television.
New York University. Office of Radio and Television.
Arrangement
The materials in Series I are arranged chronologically. The files in Series II, subseries A, B and C are arranged alphabetically by folder. In Subseries D, original order has been maintained.
The files are grouped into two series:
Series I: Records of Manager for Broadcasting Ralph Rourke
Series II: Office of Radio and Television General Files
Scope and Content Note
Series I consists of the correspondence files of Ralph Rourke, Associate Manager for Broadcasting between 1968 and 1982. Arranged chronologically, it encompasses the period between 1968 and 1982. These files also include materials describing programs, public relations activities, lectures, ceremonies, and other related topics. The focus of these records is on the public face of the University and project maintenance. They also include scripts, reports and files related to inquiries and solicitations.
Series II contains of general subject files of the Office of Radio and Television dating from 1953 to 1980. Materials in subseries A, B and C pertain to the management of specific television and radio shows. They include materials on research, public relations, arrangement with hosts and guests, recording schedules, memos, scripts, program outlines, news clippings, and press releases. Included in these documented programs is the NYU lecture series and the Arthur K. Salomon lecture, which broadcast speeches by prominent individuals made on the NYU campus. Many of the educational programs and talk shows emphasized an urban theme in keeping with the University's emphasis on building a positive public image as an exciting urban campus. These subseries illustrate both the educational and public relations functions of radio and television at New York University and reflect program management activities as well as administrative functions of the office. Subseries D contains files from the NYU Office of Public Affairs, of which the Office of Radio of Television is part, from 1976-1982. They are subject files arranged in chronological order. The subseries consists of correspondence, memos, press releases, drawing and diagrams, maps and charts, plans and blueprints. It deals with the administrative and functional aspects of the NYU Office of Public Affairs.
Historical Note
The Office of Radio and Television was created in 1952 to oversee the development of University-sponsored and -produced radio and television programs. In addition to producing educational programs, the Office of Radio and Television advised NYU faculty members on developing their prospective programs. The office also acted as a liaison between NYU and the media.
Between 1957 and 1980, the Office of Radio and Television underwent several changes of administrative jurisdiction. On April 22, 1957, the Board of Trustees amended the New York University By-Laws to create the Office of Vice President for University Relations. In 1957, the Office of Radio and Television was one of several functions placed under the jurisdiction of the Vice President for University Relations. The director of the Office of Radio and Television, Warren A. Kraetzer, became one of the vice president's assistants. Ralph Rourke served as assistant to the director of the Office of Radio and Television from 1957-1965. In 1960, Thomas J. Brophy succeeded Kraetzer as Director of Radio and Television.
The decade from 1965-1975 saw increased administrative influence over radio and television activities. In 1965, the administrative jurisdiction of the office along with other public relations functions was transferred to the office of the Vice President for University Development, and the post of Director of Public Relations was created. The Director supervised radio and television productions and reported to the Vice President of University Development. Although the News Bureau, which included radio and television functions, was under the supervision of the Director of Public Relations, it is unclear if the News Bureau manager, Paul T. Herte, had any control over the Office of Radio and Television.
As a result of these administrative changes, the position of Director of Radio and Television disappeared, and Thomas Brophy became the assistant manager for the Office of Radio and Television. Ralph Rourke's title changed to producer/writer.
In the 1970s, the educational and public relations functions of the Radio and Television Office were divided. Brophy became "Sunrise Semester" producer, and Rourke became assistant manager for the new Bureau of Radio and Television, promoting NYU to the media, and arranging radio and television appearances for faculty and administrators.
The Office of Radio and Television underwent a third transfer of administrative jurisdiction in 1975 when a new Senior Vice President for External Affairs was appointed. His responsibilities included supervising the director of public affairs, who oversaw all public relations activities, including radio and television.
From 1975-1980 it is uncertain whether public affairs activities were supervised by a vice president, director or both. In 1975, Michael Blumenfeld is referred to as both "Director of Public Affairs" and "Vice President of Public Affairs."
Access Restrictions
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection. Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted. Please contact the University Archivists with specific questions regarding restrictions.
This collection is in
off-site storage
.
Provenance
The records were transferred to the University Archives in 1989 from the Public Affairs Office.
Separated Materials
NYU publications have been removed from the collection and filed separately with other publications. Photographs of University personnel have been placed in the New York University Archives Photo Collection. Separation sheets mark where the photos were originally filed. Unannotated press releases have been separated and are housed in the University Archives press release file. Annotated press releases have been retained and filed chronologically within this collection.
New York University. Office of Public Affairs.; Rourke, Ralph; Correspondence.; Memorandums.; New York (State) |z New York.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Scripts (documents).; Universities and colleges |x Public relations.
- Series I: Records of Manager for Broadcasting Ralph Rourke, 1960-1982
  - Personal Correspondence, 1960-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - General Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - General Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - General Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - General Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - General Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - General Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1953-1980
  - Subseries A: Subject Files
    Scope and Contents
    This subseries consists of records of the Office of Radio and Television from 1953 to 1980. The materials are arranged chronologically within each file. The files are arranged alphabetically, though only files "E" through "Science" are represented. The major portion of the records are memos, scripts, prospectus cue sheets, handwritten notes, program outlines, news clippings, and press releases. They show the program management of specific shows, including research, public relations, arrangement with hosts and guests, and recording schedules.
    The collection does include some information about administrative functions of the office of Radio and Television, primarily its connection to the University Press Office.
    These records illustrate how the office of Radio and Television worked in the realms of both education and public relations. In addition, as many of the programs dealt with current events, the series provides more general historical information.
    Materials containing information on Get Involved!, a program sponsored by The Women's City Club of New York, exist in the collection. The program ran from 1969 to 1970 and was designed to bring important issues of the day to the public; topics included urban decay, women's rights and racial tension.
    Also documented is The Lively Arts, a 1964 program which centered on cultural events of the times.
    Other documents describe the radio station's lecture series, in which speeches made on the NYU campus were edited and broadcast. The files include speeches made by Isaac Asimov, A. M. Rosenthal (Managing Editor of The New York Times) and Gerald G. Glasser (NYU Professor of Business Statistics.) Other lectures include those made by former President Lyndon Johnson at the 1971 Arthur K. Salomon lecture and by former Secretary of State Henry Kissinger at the 1977 Arthur K. Salomon Lecture.
    The subseries also documents Masterbuilders of America, a program running from 1963-1964 that focused on the history of engineering in the United States. The show evidences the University's interest in television as an educational medium. The show was a joint effort with NBC, whose contract did not allow for the show to be rebroadcast and who destroyed the tapes; as such, these files provide some of the only access to the shows. Most of the administrative information is found in the files entitled "Reports."
    - The Eating Experience, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Get Involved, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Get Involved Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Get Involved Program Information, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Get Involved Work File, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Implosion; The Communications Revolution, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - History of NYU Office of Radio and Television, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - In and Out of Focus, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - In and Out of Focus, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Investor's League, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - IRS/NYU Tax Program, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - The Learning Experience, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Leaves of Grass, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Lebost Space Windmill, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Lebost Space Windmill Clippings, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - The Lively Arts, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - The Lively Arts Correspondence, 1963-1965 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Lively Lens, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Making It Count, 1972-1976 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Making It Count, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Masterbuilders of America, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Masterbuilders of America, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Masterbuilders of America, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Masterbuilders of America, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Masterbuilders of America Background, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Masterbuilders of America Meeting Notes, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Masterbuilders of America Program Notes, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Masterbuilders of America Publicity, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Masterbuilders of America Working Papers, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Measure of Democracy, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Measure of Democracy, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Miller, Maurice, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Mind Your Own Business, 1977-1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Mother of Invention, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Music and Drama in Opera, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Nine Lives, 1967-1969 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Nine Lives, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Nothing But Biography, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Nothing But Biography, 1972-1974 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - NYU Audio, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - NYU Audio, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - NYU Audio Scripts and Notes, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - NYU Audio Scripts and Notes, 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - NYU Documentary: The Dream that Grew, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1974-1976 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1975-1977 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - NYU Lecture Series Repeats, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - NYU Lecture Series Key Issues Forum, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - NYU Lecture Series Perspectives in American Law, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - NYU Lecture Series Perspectives in American Law, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Reports, 1962-1969 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Reports, 1968-1973 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Reports, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Reports, 1971-1973 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Reports, 1973-1977 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Reports, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Road Show, 1970-1971 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Russian Leviathan, 1966-1969 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Salomon Lecture/Johnson, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Salomon Lecture/Kissinger, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Salomon Lecture/Kissinger, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - SCE Radio Activity, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - School of Social Work, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Science and Engineering Television Journal, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Science Fair Series, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Sex Education Material, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Subseries B: Subject Files
    This subseries consists of records of the Office of Radio and Television from 1956-1980. The materials are arranged chronologically within each file. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence, memos, scripts, prospectuses, cue sheets, handwritten notes, program outlines, news clippings and press releases. These records reflect program management activities rather than administrative functions or policy decisions. They are primarily concerned with program research, public relations, arranging hosts and guests, and recording productions.
    This subseries illustrates both the educational and public relations functions of radio and television at New York University. Many educational programs and talk shows emphasized an urban theme in keeping with the University's concern for building a positive public image of itself as an exciting, urban campus. The increasing importance of the Office of Radio and Television as a public relations vehicle is evident in the records of "Wisdom Bank," a clearinghouse for promoting media appearances by NYU faculty and administrators and of "College Career Clinic."
    Although the collection does not fully document the Sunrise Semester program, several files contain materials pertaining to the program. The materials also document the management of the University Broadcast Lab, a series of programs developed and produced by NYU students. Students wrote, directed, and performed original works and adaptations of well-known plays. The records of University Broadcast Lab include production meeting notes, which show organizational methods and the students' relations with faculty advisors and administration.
    - Advertising and Media, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Advertising and Media, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Advertising and Media Materials, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - American Experiment WNBC-TV, 1972-1976 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - American Experiment WNBC-TV, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - American Pursuit, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - America's Town Meeting of the Air, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - American Woman, WNBC-TV, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - American Woman, WNBC-TV, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - American woman, WNBC-TV, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Audio Syndication Service, 1967-1975 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Audio Syndication Service, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Audio Syndication Service, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Beckett Festival, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Beckett Festival, 1978-1979 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Beep, Beep, Beep-Bop. The Numbers Game, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Bible Impact Today WHN Radio Series, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Bicentennial: A Black Perspective, 1975-1977 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Bicentennial: A Black Perspective, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Bicentennial: A Black Perspective, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Black Arts WCBS-TV, 1971-1972 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Black Letters WCBS-TV, 1968-1975 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Black Letters WCBS-TV, 1968-1969 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Black Letters WCBS-TV, 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Black Letters WCBS-TV, undated (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Black Letters WCBS-TV, 1968-1969 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Black Letters WCBS-TV, 1969-1970 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Black Letters WCBS-TV, 1970-1971 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Black Oriented Materials, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Bobst Library Dedication, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Brainstorm, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Budget Expenses, 1961-1965 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Budget Expenses, 1968-1970 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Budget Expenses, 1970-1971 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Budget Expenses, 1971-1972 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Budget Expenses, 1972-1973 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Budget Expenses, 1973-1974 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Budget Expenses, 1974-1925 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Budget Expenses, 1975-1976 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Campus Dateline/College Call-In CICU Project, 1976-1979 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Career Mail, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Children and All That Jazz, 1978-1980 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Children and All That Jazz, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Children and All That Jazz, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Children and All That Jazz, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Children and All That Jazz, undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - The Chief Executive, 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - College Career Clinic, 1960 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - College Career Clinic, 1960 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - College Career Clinic, 1960 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Commission on Independent Colleges and Universities (CICU), 1977 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Consultants at Large, 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Consultants at Large, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Corporation for Public Broadcasting, 1972-1979 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Cott, Betty, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Cue WNBC-TV, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Culture Break, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Dateline History WABC, 1962-1963 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Dedication of the Brookdale Center, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Economic Viewpoint, 1968-1970 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Edel, Leon, 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Eisenbud Book Promotion, 1978-1979 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Environmental Research Material, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Film: Basic Equipment and Budget, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Film: Oil Slick Control and Air Pollution Research, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Film: Production Permission, 1969-1978 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Fordham Formats, 1956-1957 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Freedom's Word, 1980 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Lets Talk Psychology, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - NYU Stock Exchange, 1962 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1973-1974 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1924 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1974-1977 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1974-1975 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1972-1973 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1971-1972 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1970-1971 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1966-1968 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1962-1968 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1968-1970 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1968-1969 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - NYU Lecture Series, 1968-1969 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - NYU TV Production Center: ETMA, 1961-1962 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - NYU TV Production Center: ETMA, 1962 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Next Stop: College, 1963-1967 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - North Star, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - The Numbers Game, 1968-1969 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Office Skills Unlimited, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - One To One, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - One To One, 1972-1973 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - One To One, 1973 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - One To One, 1972 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - One To One, 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - One To One, 1970-1971 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - One To One, 1970-1971 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - One To One, 1969-1970 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - One To One, 1969-1970 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - One To One, 1968-1969 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Our Cultural Heritage, 1977-1978 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Our Legal Profile, 1964-1966 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Our Legal Profile, 1964 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Our Legal Profile, 1964-1965 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Our Legal Profile, 1964-1965 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Our Legal Profile, 1964 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Our Legal Profile, undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Our Legal Profile, undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Our Legal Profile, undated (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Our Legal Profile, undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Our Legal Profile, undated (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Our Legal Profile, 1964-1965 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Our Legal Profile, 1964-1966 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Patterns, 1970 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Perspectives in American Law WNYC-AM, 1976-1977 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Press Notices, 1954, 1969, 1975 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Production: Expenses, 1966-1970 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Public Broadcast Laboratory, 1967-1968 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Public Service Announcements, 1968-1977 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Public Service Announcement, 1978 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Public Service Announcements, undated (Box 21, Folder 12)